Guide to the Brooklyn Society of Artists records 1997.080
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Society of Artists records
1941 to 1965
1952-1957
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Society of Artists (New York, N.Y.)
Losey, Elizabeth
1997.080
0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
The records consist of correspondence, administrative files, membership lists, and exhibition records, dating from 1941 to 1965.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Related Materials
The Brooklyn Museum holds one folder on the Brooklyn Society of Artists in its Brooklyn Museum of Art Library Collections, BMA institutional files.
The Archives of American Art holds the Nancy Sussman Ranson papers, 1925-1971, which includes material related to the Brooklyn Society of Artists.
Arrangement
The records are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Folder titles are derived from their original labels.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, administrative files, membership lists, and exhibition records, dating from 1941 to 1965. The records include the files of two of the society's presidents, Mary Kellner and Nancy Ranson.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were donated to the Brooklyn Historical Society in 1997 by Elizabeth Losey. The records were originally in the possession of Elizabeth Erlanger, then inherited by her daughter, Jeane Erlanger Jonas, who passed them on her to daughter, Ms. Losey.
Historical note
The Brooklyn Society of Artists was founded in 1917. According to The History of the American Society of Contemporary Artists, by Frank Mann and Charles Keller, "charter members were committed to creating an exhibiting organization dedicated to the broadening of opportunity for artists to display their work." While membership in the society was originally limited to arists living or working in the borough of Brooklyn, its constitution was amended in 1919 to extend membership to artists living in the greater New York area. Its first exhibition was held in 1919 at Brooklyn's Pouch Gallery. Later exhibition venues included Abraham and Straus, Pratt Institute, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Academy of Music, Riverside Museum, and the Lever House. By the 1950s, the society was curating traveling exhibitions and issuing scholarships. In 1963, the society officially changed its name to the American Society of Contemporary Artists (ASCA).
Based on The History of the American Society of Contemporary Artists by Frank Mann and Charles Keller.
Programs (documents); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Administrative records; Art |x Exhibitions; Correspondence; Art |x Societies, etc.; Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Losey, Elizabeth; Ranson, Nancy Sussman; Riverside Museum (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Museum; Union Dime Savings Bank; Kellner, Mary
- Applications, 1953 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 1)
- Award Data, 1950-1955 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 2)
- Ballots, 1952-1955 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 3)
- Brooklyn Museum, 1948-1956 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 4)
- Charter, 1952-1954 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence (2 folders), 1941-1957, 1965 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 6-7)
- Exhibition: Union Dime Savings Bank, 1955-1956 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 8)
  General
  Ruth Irish, Assistant Manager; Jan. 19 reception; Jan. 23 opening; Feb. 6 closing
- Meeting: Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims, 1953-1956 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 9)
- Membership Lists and Patron Members, 1951-1957 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 10)
- Mary Kellner - President, 1952-1954 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 11)
- Nancy Ransom - President, 1954-1956 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 12)
- 38th Annual Exhibition - Riverside Museum, Oct. 31 - Nov. 21 1954 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 13)
- 39th Annual Exhibition - Riverside Museum, Apr. 15-24 1955 (Box 1 of 1, Folder 14)